宇宙是灵魂的镜子
Space is the mirror of the soul.
我们是瞭望远方  还是照进内心呢
Are we looking beyond, or are we looking within?
我是看向鞋子
I'm looking at my shoes.
我都看得有点晕乎了
This is making me a little motion sick.
当我们凝望着无止尽的宇宙
When we gaze out at the immensities of space,
我们能了解它  是因为我们的内心
we understand them because there are immensities
也是无限大
within us as well.
我是拉杰什·库萨帕里博士
I'm Dr. Rajesh Koothrappali,
感谢各位与我一起
and thank you for taking a walk with me...
漫步群星之中
through the stars.
他收尾的停顿  一次比一次长
That pause gets longer every show.
我觉得...
I believe...
你说得没错
you're right.
你好
Hey.
我能跟你合照一张吗
Can I get a picture with you?
没问题
Absolutely.
如果你要发到社交平台
And if you post it on social media,
我建议你加个话题#库萨诗里#
I suggest the hashtag "Koothra-poet."
谢谢你  节目很棒
Thank you. The show was great.
这不全是我一个人的功劳
Well, I can't take all the credit.
我有一群很棒的明星配角
I have pretty good co-stars.
一群明"星"
The stars.
你对每个人都说这套词吗
Do you say that to everyone?
只对美女
Only to beautiful women.
还有还行的女孩说
And okay women.
行吧
Okay.
我澄清一下  你是前一类人
Uh, just to clarify: you're the first kind.
行吧
Okay.
谢谢你们来
Thanks for coming.
两位帅哥对今晚的节目有何评价
What did you handsome gentlemen think of the show?
你可以收功了
Uh, you can turn it off now.
谢谢夸奖  但我的魅力能放不能收
It's sweet of you to say, but I don't think I can.
第十一季  第十四集
看看这张哈雷在泡澡的超萌照片
Look at this cute picture of Halley in the bath.
拍得很赞啊
Aw, that's great.
要我发给你吗
Want me to send it to you?
别了  在你手机是可爱  在我手机上是犯罪
No, on your phone it's cute, on my phone it's a crime.
我也有一张很萌的照片分享
I also have a pretty cute picture to share.
那是什么
What is that?
一个方程式
An equation.
它是不是太完美了
Isn't it perfect?
有时候我就这么盯着它看
Sometimes I just stare at it,
心想"真想不到它是我孕育出来的"
and I think "I can't believe that came out of me."
既然我们要分享照片
Well, since we're sharing pictures,
我也可以贡献一张
I have one to contribute.
拜托别是你跟你狗一起泡澡的照片
Please don't let it be you and your dog in the bathtub.
并不是
It's not.
但别滑去看别张照片
But don't swipe.
这是什么
What are we looking at here?
是我跟一个美女的合照
Well, that's me and a beautiful woman
而从我的手表可以看出是半夜两点半拍的
and my watch showing the time as 2:30 in the morning.
所以... 证物"A"吗
So, state's exhibit "A"?
不是啦  我前几天跟她在天文台认识的
No. I met her at the planetarium a few days ago,
她后来邀请我出去喝一杯
and she invited me out for a drink.
那恭喜你啊
Oh, good for you. H-Hey,
印地语的"狗"怎么说
w-what's the Hindi word for "dog"?
-库塔  -你这只贱库塔
- Kutta. - You kutta.
咆咆
Bow-bow.
这是印地语的汪汪
That's Hindi for woof-woof.
我今晚跟她又有约
I am seeing her again tonight.
我今晚也有约呢
You know, I also have a date tonight.
但别担心  不是跟别的女人
But don't worry, it's not another woman.
是跟弦理论有约
It's string theory.
咆咆
Bow-bow.
抱歉  但人家才是色库塔  你不算
Sorry, he's a kutta, you're not.
-回来了  -回来啦
- Hi. - Hello.
你在干嘛
What you doing?
跟我的宝宝合照
Oh, taking another picture with my baby.
你看它长多大了
Look how big he got.
看到你这么兴奋挺有意思的
It's fun to see you this excited.
谢谢啦  你人...
Aw, thank you, that's so...
-不许坐这里  -啥  怎么了
- Don't sit there! ?- What, what?
抱歉啦
I, uh-- sorry.
这是我归类系统的一部分
I-It's part of my organization system.
那里是我放论文的地方
That's-that's where those papers go.
好吧  那不如我...
Okay. Um, how about if I just...
把这笔记本推过去...
slide this notebook...
行吧  没关系
You know what, it's fine.
我去卧室里待着
I'll just be in the bedroom.
不用  别  这里也是你的公寓
No, no. Uh, this is your apartment, too.
我今晚收工吧
Uh, look, I'll-I'll stop for the night
然后把这里收拾了
and clean this up.
你真是太贴心了  谢尔顿
Well, that's very considerate, Sheldon.
我知道
I know.
其实我是在尝试一个新招式
See, I'm trying this new technique
就是我换位思考  做到感同身受
where I imagine how I would feel in someone else's position.
你是指同理心吗
Y-You mean empathy?
我还以为这是我发明的新方法呢
Oh, I thought I came up with it.
无论如何  我还是谢谢你做出的努力
Well, regardless, I-I appreciate the effort.
谢谢
Thank you.
真的很难呢
It's really hard.
早安
Morning.
早安啊
Good morning.
你其实不用为我做早餐
Aw, you didn't have to cook me breakfast.
我不确定我昨晚的表现如何
Well, I wasn't sure how I did last night,
我想确定有个强劲的收尾
and I wanted to finish strong.
你不用担心啦
You don't need to worry.
昨晚很赞了
Last night was great.
虽然你现在这么说
Ah, well, you say that now,
但等你吃过一口之后再发表意见
but wait until you taste this.
我的天  太好吃了吧
Oh, my God, this is amazing.
所以我在后车厢里都有备一个煎蛋锅
Which is why I keep an omelet pan in the trunk of my car.
谢谢啦  很好吃
Well, thank you, it's delicious.
我老公从来不做饭给我吃
My husband never cooked for me.
你结过婚了吗
Oh, uh, y-you were married.
是啊  严格上来说我还已婚
Yeah. Well, technically, I guess I still am.
你的"严格上来说"
Is that "technically,"
是指离婚文件还没正式生效
like, the paperwork hasn't gone through,
还是"严格上来说"
or "technically,"
他现在正在衣柜里看着我们俩
like, he's in the closet watching us right now?
没有啦  我们已经分居了
No, no, we're separated.
我们能聊一点别的吗
Do you mind if we talk about something else?
当然啦
Of course.
告诉你  我的煎蛋卷能这么好吃的秘诀
Uh, you know, my secret to making great omelets is that
是我把蛋黄跟蛋白是分开打散
I beat the egg whites separately.
说到这个  你们分开多久了
Speaking of which, how long have you been separated?
大概两周吧
About two weeks.
这周数不太多啊
That is not a lot of weeks.
其实这刚刚过了双数周数的门槛啊
In fact, that's the bare minimum to get to the plural "weeks."
无所谓啊
Doesn't matter.
他已搬走  我向前走
He moved out, I moved on.
很好
Oh. Good.
你介意我问一下他是干哪一行的吗
Yeah, do you mind me asking what he does for a living?
他是消防员
He's a firefighter.
有意思
Oh. Interesting.
一个有可能妒火中烧  还善用斧子的男人
A potentially jealous man who's handy with an ax.
不过没事的啦
It's-it's okay, though.
他可是有将近整整两周时间冷静呢
He's almost had two weeks to cool down.
好的  下一款药是罗马唑
Okay, the next drug is Romatrol.
这款我会
Oh, I know this one.
我其实很努力在推销这款药呢
We're actually pushing it really hard.
它能治疗轻微皮肤炎
It treats mild dermatitis.
正确  这款药能开给哪些人群呢
Uh, correct. And who can it be prescribed to?
成人  以及百分百确定
Adults and children who have absolutely, for sure,
已经停止生长的孩子
stopped growing.
再次正确
Right again.
有哪些副作用呢
And what are the side effects?
靠  靠
Oh, shoot, shoot.
想一下助记词
Mm, remember the mnemonic.
肉汁G  R  A  V  Y
Ah-- GRAVY, yes. G-R-A-V-Y.
胃部不适  红肿
Okay, gastric distress, redness,
肛漏  血管炎  还有...
anal leakage, vasculitis and...
黄眼
yellow eyes.
很接近了
Oh, uh, so close.
-是黄带[白带发黄]  -对哦
- It's actually yellow discharge. - Oh, right.
所以我们用"肉汁"这个词
That's why we went with "Gravy."
他知道自己现在不住在这里的吧
He knows he doesn't live here anymore, right?
可能他失忆了  因为他吃了...
Maybe he's experiencing memory loss because he took...
-弗拉西崔  -正解
- Flaxitrite. - Yeah.
-谢啦  -谢尔顿  你在干嘛
- Thank you. - Uh, Sheldon, what are you doing?
我就过来看一下我的旧房间
Oh, I was just checking in on my old room
看看你们怎么处置它
to see what you've done with it.
怎么了
Why?
我晚上需要一个地方工作  而且...
Well, I could use a place to work in the evenings, and...
-不  -因为
- No. - Well, it's just that
-我们公寓没有多余的地方  -不
- there's not a lot of space in our apartment... - No.
我觉得艾米一直有...
Well, and I feel like Amy's been having...
不
No.
反正你们也不...
And since you're not...
不
No.
就...
It's...
不
No.
现在那是我们的房间
That is our room now,
而且我们要把它变成健身房
and we're gonna turn it into a gym.
你们真的觉得我会信这种鬼话吗
Do you really expect me to believe that?
-不  -不
- No. - No.
所以现在让我困扰的是
So I guess what's bugging me
他们13天前才分手
is that they only broke up 13 days ago,
现在我却在跟她交往
and now I'm dating her.
那我是我人生电影里的好人
So, am I, like, the good guy in my movie,
还是他们人生电影里的坏人呢
or the bad guy in their movie?
我能肯定你是我们人生电影里的怪友人
Pretty sure you're the weird friend in our movie.
我喜欢她  好吗
I like her, okay?
我只是...不知道该如何看待自己
I just, I-I don't know how I feel about
在一段感情里充当电灯泡的角色
being the third wheel in a relationship.
跟我老婆躺在一张床上的某人如是说
Says the guy in my bed with my wife.
我的意思是  她老公还没走远呢
Guys, I mean, he's around, okay?
他很显然对分手耿耿于怀
He's apparently not happy about the breakup,
而且从他留在她家的运动裤可以判断出
and based on the sweatpants he left at her place,
这家伙至少是个中等到彪形大汉
he's, like, a medium to large man.
或许那是他的"假日发福后"专用裤
Maybe those are his "after the holiday" pants,
你也有啊
like you have.
我也不知道了
I don't know.
你们觉得她是不是太快开始约会了
I mean, do you think it's too soon for her to be dating?
如果你和伯纳黛特分手了
If you and Bernadette broke up,
你会等多久才开始约会
like, how long would you wait?
我都不想去想这种问题
Oh, well, I don't even want to think...
八天
Eight days.
什么
What?
在家哭两天  健身房恢复身材六天
Two days to cry. Six days to hit the gym.
首先你身材已经很棒了
First of all, you already look amazing.
嘴真甜
Aw, that's sweet.
那我再多为他哭一天吧
I'm gonna give him an extra day of crying.
不就是不
The answer is still no.
随你说我们不会察觉到你在  但我们就是能
You can say we wouldn't know you're here, but we'd know.
因为你就会在这里啊
Because you'd be here!
是谁的电话呀
So, who was that?
真不敢相信你居然挂我电话
I can't believe you hung up on me!
什么鬼
What the hell?
你在我们家干嘛
What are you doing here?
我是来证明你是错的
I am proving you wrong.
我已经在里面工作好几个小时了
I've been working back there for hours.
你们根本没察觉
You had no idea.
帮帮忙
Do something.
什么鬼  你在我们家干嘛
What the hell? What are you doing here?
我在试着尊重艾米
I-I am trying to respect Amy.
好吧  你在学校有自己的办公室
Okay, look, you have an office at work.
你怎么不去那办公
Why don't you go there?
我不能每次一有灵感就冲去学校办公室啊
I can't go to the office every time I have a brilliant thought.
那我岂不是相当于住那儿了
I'd basically be living there.
听起来不错  去吧
Sounds good, do that.
不行  校园晚上不安全
No. No, the campus isn't safe at night.
那里不但有浣熊  还有大学生到处走
There's raccoons and undergrads just walking around
好像那是他们的地盘一样
like they own the place.
听着
Look.
我需要一个可以晚上工作的地方
I need somewhere to work in the evenings.
而你们正好有不用的房间
You have a space you aren't using.
看一眼我的提议
Just take a look at my proposal.
这是什么
What is this?
租赁协议
A rental agreement.
这间房间我仅用于办公
I will only use the room for work.
我不会睡这里  我不会吃你们的食物
I-I won't sleep here, I won't eat your food,
我甚至不会用你们的洗手间
I won't even use your bathroom.
你从此就能无论白天黑夜想来就来吗
So you can just walk in any time of the day or night?
他现在不就这样吗
Well, he does that now.
至少签了协议我们还有钱拿
At least this way we'll get paid.
我是拉杰什·库萨帕里博士
I am Dr. Rajesh Koothrappali,
感谢各位与我一起
and thank you for taking a walk with me...
...漫步群星之中
...through the stars.
我觉得刚才那停顿太长了
I-I think that one was too long.
你说得对  我也感觉到了
Yeah, you're right. I totally felt it.
我们要不再来一遍
Should we, uh, run it again?
天啊  不要了吧
Please, God, no.
需要帮忙吗
Can I help you?
你们俩谁是拉杰什·库萨帕里
Which one of you is Rajesh Koothrappali?
不是吧  你看不出来
Really? You're not sure
我们俩谁是拉杰什·库萨帕里吗
which one of us is Rajesh Koothrappali?
看出来了  我只是不想弄得像种族歧视
I am. I was just trying not to be racist.
我是妮尔的老公
I'm Nell's husband.
是这样的  我真不知道
h-here's the thing-- I didn't know
她已经结婚了  是事后...
that she was married until after...
什么事之后
After what?
我
I'm...
真的非常对不起
I'm really sorry.
道歉并不会让我好过点
Well, that doesn't make me feel better.
那做什么能让你好过点
Wh-What would make you feel better?
我要你不再和我老婆来往
I want you to stop seeing my wife.
没问题  很高兴认识你  再见
Done. Nice to meet you. Bye.
我该怎么办
What am I gonna do?
大兄弟  你想聊聊吗
Hey, buddy, do-do you want to talk?
我本以为我们会结婚生子
I thought we were gonna start a family.
没想到措不及防  感情玩完
Next thing I know, it's over.
一切都会好的
It's gonna be okay.
怎么可能会好
How is it gonna be okay?
你睡了我老婆
You're sleeping with my wife.
我是说  除了这事之外
I mean, besides that.
你需要点什么吗
Can I get you anything?
来杯水
A glass of water?
还是来场激光秀
A laser show?
-不必  谢了  -太好了
No, thank you. ?Oh, good.
因为我根本不知道开关在哪
'Cause I don't, I don't even know how to turn it on.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
我不该来这里
I shouldn't have come here.
可能我只是想看看取代我的人是谁
I guess I just wanted to see who she replaced me with.
别这么说
Don't say that.
你们俩的感情很特别
What you two had was special.
谁也取代不了你
No one can replace you.
这话是她说的吗
Did she say that?
不是
No.
我该走了  对吧
I should go, right?
别走
Stay.
好的  晚点联系
Okay, I'll call you later.
听着  如果这么说能让你好过点
Look, if it makes you feel any better,
我跟她一点都不熟
I barely know her.
不熟她还跟你睡吗
And she had sex with you?
妮尔说你是名消防员
Nell tells me you're a fireman.
都做些什么呀
What's that like?
好吧  知道他在房间里面
Okay, I-I-I'm really uncomfortable
我真的很不舒服
with him back in that room.
为什么  他一天都没出来了
Why? He hasn't made a peep all day.
你不懂
Y-Y-You don't get it.
我跟谢尔顿住了那么多年
All the years that we lived together,
他总是能把我弄疯
he drove me crazy the whole time.
而现在却乖乖的
And now he's not.
对啊
Exactly.
别用那种眼神看着我
D-Don't look at me like that.
这代表他是故意的
It-it-it means he did it on purpose.
那是他的选择
It was a choice.
就像发现哥斯拉本来可以吃个阿比三明治
That-That's like finding out Godzilla could've had Arby's
结果却故意去毁东京一样
instead of Tokyo.
我想日本应该没有阿比三明治店
I don't think they have Arby's in Japan.
这不是重点
Not my point.
谢尔顿
Sheldon.
Sheldon!
抱歉  我是不是太大声了
I'm sorry. Am I being too loud?
不是  你表现得很完美  你心知肚明
No, you're being perfect and you know it.
你希望我当一个不那么良心的租客吗
Would you like me to be a less considerate tenant?
不是  是的  什...
No. Yes. What...?
别再逼疯我了
Stop messing with me!
我错了
Hey, I was wrong.
阿比三明治在冲绳有分店
There's an Arby's in Okinawa.
他以前跟她哥哥是死党
He was best friends with her older brother,
但他当时根本没注意到她
but he didn't even notice her.
几年后
And then years afterward,
他们在车管所偶遇了对方
they randomly bumped into each other at the DMV.
两小时后  他们就坠入爱河了
Two hours later, they were in love.
你能从他驾驶证照片中看到眼里爱的火花
You can really see the sparkle in his license photo.
这些都是他在天文馆跟你说的吗
He told you all this at the planetarium?
不不  我们去馅饼屋了
No, no, we went to House of Pies.
他点了香蕉奶油  我点了椰子口味
He got banana cream. I got coconut.
我们分着吃
We did halfsies.
你跟另一个男人分吃一块馅饼吗
You did pie halfsies with another man?
你是指除你以外的男人吗
You mean other than you?
是啊
Yeah.
我很同情他  妮妮
I feel bad for him, Bernie.
他是个好人
He's a, he's a good guy.
如果你觉得不舒服
Well, if you're uncomfortable with it,
也许就别再跟他老婆上床了
maybe stop sleeping with his wife.
我觉得性不是问题所在
I don't think the sex is the problem.
我很肯定相比起来我表现一般
I know for a fact I was just okay.
我想说馅饼屋这店是我带你认识的
For the record, I'm the one who introduced you to House of Pies.
谢尔顿
Sheldon?
是莱纳德啊
Oh, Leonard.
抱歉  我必须离开那里
Sorry, I just, I had to get out of there.
他又做了什么
What did he do now?
啥都没做  他简直是天使
Nothing. He's being a dream.
别那样看着我
Don't give me that look.
佩妮就是用那种眼神看我  我没疯
That's how Penny looked at me. I'm not crazy.
佩妮和我的"你疯了"眼神一样吗
Penny and I have the same "You're crazy" look?
好甜好有爱
That's kind of sweet.
我懂得如何对付真实的谢尔顿
I know how to deal with Sheldon being Sheldon,
但表现得理智又体贴的谢尔顿
but Sheldon being a-a rational, thoughtful person?
我都懵了
I'm clueless. I-It's like
就像去年我妈打给我  唱生日歌给我听
when my mom called last year to sing happy birthday
我直接吐了
and I-I just threw up.
如果太难以忍受
Well, if it gets to be too much,
你随时可以把他赶回来这里
you can always send him back over here.
我和他说好了
I made a deal with him,
再说  那样对你不公平
and besides, that wouldn't be fair to you.
实际上  我挺想他的
Well, actually, I miss him.
他最近都泡在那边
He's been over there a lot.
太好了  那告诉他他可以回来了
Well, great. Tell him he can come back.
不行  他在为我和我的感受着想
I can't. He's thinking of me and my feelings
他想尊重我
and trying to be respectful.
他也是那样对我的  那混蛋
That's what he's doing to me, too, the jerk!
别再露出那眼神了
Stop that.
你生气的表情和谢尔顿便秘的表情是一样的
Hey, your mad look and Sheldon's constipated look are the same.
这感觉真好
This is nice.
是的
It is.
她以前也是这样吻我的
She used to kiss me like that.
你还好吧
You okay?
没事  抱歉
Yeah. Yeah, I'm sorry.
没事
Yeah.
老天啊  我好孤单啊
Oh, God, I'm so alone.
抱歉  我没办法
Sorry, I can't do this.
怎么了
What's going on?
我前几天遇到奥利弗了
I met Oliver the other day.
等等  你去找我老公了吗
Wait, you tracked down my husband?
不是  那多奇怪啊
No, that would be weird.
是他来找我  然后我们共度了一晚
He tracked me down, then we spent the evening together.
真难以置信
I don't believe this.
他那样做都是因为他在乎你
He-he only did it because he cares about you.
不  是因为他占有欲强  又爱吃醋
No, he did it because he's possessive and jealous.
真的吗  我完全没看出来
Really? I didn't get that at all.
他让我感到很舒服自在
He made me feel very comfortable.
你俩"基"出火花  我倍感欣慰啊
Well, I'm glad you two hit it off.
其实  我觉得你对他不公平
You know, I don't think that you're being very fair to him.
你站他那边吗
You're taking his side?
没有  但我要指出
No, but I should point out that
他提议过做婚姻咨询  所以至少他在努力挽回
he did offer to go to counseling, so at least one of you is trying.
你比他还神经病
You're crazier than he is.
这样吧  你再给他一次机会
I'll tell you what, just give him one more chance
如果还是不成功
and if it doesn't work out,
我很乐意继续和你打炮
I'll be happy to keep sleeping with you.
你很乐意是吧
You would?
不管哪种结果  你都会有男人
Either way, you've got yourself a fella.
这多棒啊
Like, how nice is that?
谢尔顿
Hey, Sheldon.
你好
Hello.
你的合同规定有三天试用期
So, your contract provides for a three-day trial period,
我觉得这事还是行不通
and I don't think this is working out.
所以  用法律术语来说
So, to put it in legal terms,
就是合同甲方
the party of the first part would like
希望合同乙方滚蛋
the party of the second part to get out.
试用期几点结束
What time does the trial period end?
中午12点
12:00, noon.
那后面还写了什么
Yeah-- what does it say after that?
剧中主角所在的西部比东部慢三小时
东部标准时间
Eastern Standard Time.
那是3小时前的事了
That was three hours ago.
既然你没有行使废除合约的权利
And, uh, since you didn't exercise your right to revoke,
我要行使我的权利来延长合约
I exercised my right to extend,
这令这份超详细的租赁合同开始生效
triggering this long-form rental agreement...
而你已经违反了上面的条约
...of which you're already in violation.
这不过是一堆纸张
This is just a-a bunch of paper.
你无法强制执行
You can't enforce this.
请个律师  我们见分晓
Hire a lawyer. Let's find out.
这事不是真的
This is not happening.
随你怎么想
Be that as it may,
但第九页写着你得为我提供
page nine says that you have to provide me
柠檬味的气泡水  所以赶紧的
with lemon-flavored sparkling waters, so... chop-chop.
结果如何
Hey, how'd it go?
显然他是不会走了
Well, apparently he's not leaving
而我还得给他弄气泡水来
and I have to go get him sparkling water.
你为什么在笑
Why are you smiling?
我也不知道  就是感觉对了
I don't know. It just feels right.
漫步群星之中
...through the stars.
你好啊  兄弟
Hey, buddy.
我和妮尔谈过了
I talked to Nell.
你走了之后她很不高兴
She was pretty upset after you left.
-我很抱歉  -不  不不
- Yeah, I'm sorry. - No. No, no, no.
她说你说了一些很诡异变态的话
She told me that you said something so creepy
相比之下  我显得很棒
that I seemed great in comparison.
我知道是哪句话
I know exactly what it was.
不  其实
I... no, actually,
有几句都有可能
there was a couple of things it could've been.
无论是哪句  都很诡异变态
Whichever one it was, it was creepy.
总之  我去安慰了她
Anyway, uh, I went over to comfort her,
我们谈了一下  貌似我们会再给彼此一次机会
and we talked, and I think we're gonna give it another chance.
我真为你高兴
I'm so happy for you!
我们应该庆祝一下
We should celebrate.
去馅饼屋吗
House of Pies?
那还用说吗
You know it.
要叫上妮尔吗
Should we invite Nell?
有必要吗
Do we have to?
算了吧
Nah.